Register of the Brian Crozier Papers, 1936-1993
Hoover Institution Archives
Brian Crozier Papers,
1936-1993
85035
Crozier, Brian
9 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (3.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, book reviews, and printed matter, relating to the Cold War and world politics since World War II, international communism, terrorism, espionage and insurgency movements, and the Institute for the Study of Conflict.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (11 reels).
Access Points
World politics--1945-; Communism; Terrorism; Espionage; Guerrilla warfare; Institute for the Study of Conflict; Journalists; Great Britain
Biography
1918 August 4 Born, Australia
1936-1939 Music and art critic, London
1940-1941 Reporter-sub-editor, Stoke on Trent, Stockport, London
1941-1943 Aeronautical inspector
1943-1944 Sub-editor, Reuters
1944-1948 Sub-editor, News Chronicle
1948-1951 Writer, Sydney Morning Herald
1951-1952 Correspondent, Reuters-AAP
1952-1953 Features editor, Straits Times
1954-1964 Leader writer and correspondent, Economist
1954-1966 Commentator, BBC English, French and Spanish overseas services
1960 Author, The Rebels
1963 Author, The Morning After
1964 Author, Neo-Colonialism
1965 Author, South-East Asia in Turmoil
1965-1974 Chairman, Forum World Features
1966 Author, The Struggle for the Third World
1967 Author, Franco
1969 Author, The Masters of Power
1970 Author, The Future of Communist Power
1970-1979 Co-founder and director, Institute for the Study of Conflict
1970-1975 Editor, Conflict Studies
1971 Author, Since Stalin
1973 Author, De Gaulle
1974 Author, A Theory of Conflict
1976 Author, The Man Who Lost China
1978 Author, The Strategy of Survival
1979 Author, The Minimum State
1984 Author, This War Called Peace
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1937-1984. (Box 1)
  Employment records, personal letters, memoranda, conversation transcripts, press cables, and clippings. Includes speeches and writings and a press file regarding Brian Crozier, attacking him as well as the activities of the Forum World Features and of the Institute for the Study of Conflict
- CORRRESPONDENCE, 1966-1991. (Boxes 2-4)
  Correspondence divided into chronological, alphabetical, and miscellaneous VIP files. Includes some letters to the editor, memoranda, speeches, and writings
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1936-1992. (Boxes 4-9)
  Freelance writings consisting of articles, essays, letters to the editor, memoranda, newspaper columns, reviews, and related correspondence, arranged chronologically by year; and reviews of and background material for Brian Crozier's books, as well as related correspondence and letters to the editor, arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1975-1977. (Box 9)
  Parliamentary debate transcripts, clippings, and articles relating to the expulsions from Great Britain of Philip Agee and Mark Hosenball
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Photo file)
  One print depicting Belkacem Krim and one depicting Sir Robert Thompson
Container List
N.B.: Each file was established by Brian Crozier, and retained as is with its inner organization. In most cases, the file includes a detailed list of the contents compiled by Brian Crozier, often with accompanying notes and commentaries. Copies of all such lists, with corresponding box/folder numbers, can be found as an appendix to the register
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1937-1984
  - General. Employment records, personal letters, memoranda, conversation transcripts, articles, press cables, speeches, and clippings
    - 1937-1954 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - 1958-1965 (Folder 2)
  - "Great smear campaign." Press files relating to Brian Crozier, attacking him as well as the activities of the Forum World Features and the Institute for the Study of Conflict
    - 1975-1976 (Folder 3)
    - 1977-1984 (Folder 4)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1966-1991
  - General. Chronological files relating to Brian Crozier's writings and activities, political conditions in various countries, and world events. Includes some letters to the editor, memoranda, speeches, and writings
    - 1966-1968. Correspondents include James Cameron, Luis de Caralt, N. D. Clive, L. A. Crozier, Heather Dean, Cecil Eprile, Brian Melland, Maurice Temple Smith, Kenneth Younger (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - 1969. Correspondents include Brian Beedham, Max Beloff, W. A. Bradley, John Bright-Holmes, Hugo Brunner, Alastair Burnet, Jerome Ch'en, Sir Alec Douglas-Home, Francois Duchene, Georges Egal, Sir Donald Evants, Jacques Fauvet, Roger Frey, Charles G. Haering, Kenneth Hunt, Louis Joxe, Jean Olie, I. M. Parsons, David Rees, William Rees-Mogg, Jacques Richard, Leonard Schapiro, John Hay Whitney (Folder 2)
    - 1970. Correspondents include Georges Albertini, George Gale, Charles de Gaulle, Anthony Hartley, Sir William Hayter, Chaim U. Lipschitz, Henri Michel, Tibor Szamuely, Frank Treherne, Kenneth Younger (Folder 3)
    - 1971. Correspondents include Georges Albertini, William Bader, Hilaire du Berrier, Zbigniew Brzezinski, Robert W. Foster, Howard B. Gotlieb, David Higham, Jean Olie, Joaquim Marco, Dorothy Pickles, Jean Sainteny, Frank Shakespeare, Sir Edward Spears, H. H. Tucker, Richard L. Walker (Folder 4)
    - 1972. Correspondents include Georges Albertini, Gillon Aitken, Raymond Aron, Ricardo de la Cierva, Robert Conquest, Charles Douglas-Home, C. H. Ellis, Simone Gallimard, Nigel Lawson, E. H. Marsh, Lord Robens, Tibor Szamuely, John Whitehorn, Geoffrey Wolley (Folder 5)
    - 1973. Correspondents include Gillon Aitken, Georges Albertini, Julian Amery, Max Beloff, Peter Calvocoressi, C. J. Child, Maurice Cranston, M. F. Cullis, Jacques Fauvet, James FitzSimmons, Andre Fontaine, M. R. D. Foot, Lord Halsbury, Sir Archibald James, Paul Lendvai, John McCuen, Brian Melland, F. S. Miles, Robert Moss, Peter Richards, William Rees-Mogg, Rivers Scott, Harold Sieve, C. Sinclair-Stevenson, William C. Sullivan, Sir Edward Tomkins, David Watt, Simon Wiesenthal. See also 1977 (Folder 6)
    - 1974. Correspondents include Georges Albertini, David Astor, James Burnham, Lord Carrington, Cheng Yin-fun, C. Richard Cleary, Georges Egal, C. H. Ellis, Harvey Feldman, Manuel Fraga Iribarne, Lord Halsbury, Iain Hamilton, Charles Janson, Sir Keith Joseph, Viktor Lessiovski, J. M. A. Luns, William C. Mott, Malcolm Muggeridge, Aleksei Myagkov, Shih Hsin-jen, John Vernon, Peregrine Worsthorne (Folder 7)
    - 1975. Correspondents include Peter Baldwin, Hugh Beach, James Burnham, Eric Chou, O. Edmund Clubb, Judith Cooper, Decima Curtis, Sir William Deakin, C. H. Ellis, Manuel Fraga Iribarne, John Graham, Lord Home, Walter Judd, Sir John Killick, William Kintner, Frank Kitson, David Martin, S. W. B. Menaul, Robert Moss, Sir Michael Palliser, Edward Rozek, Helmut Schoeck, Robert C. Stones, Hugh Thomas, Sir Robert Thompson, Philip Toynbee, Prince Wangchuk (Folder 8)
    - 1976. Correspondents include Frank Brenchley, Zbigniew Brzezinski, James Burnham, Kenneth Cantlie, Lord Chalfont, Winston Churchill, Serge Dassault, Robert A. Fearey, Charles Forte, Sir Ian Gilmour, Hans Josef Horchem, Charles Janson, Sir John Killick, Sir Robert Mark, Burroughs Mitchell, Carlo Pesenti, P. Pooley, Gordon Reece, Robert W. Rust, Margaret Thatcher, Sir Robert Thompson, John Vernon, John Hay Whitney, Paul Wilkinson, Sir David Willison (Folder 9)
    - 1977. Correspondents include Lord Ardwick, Raymond Aron, John Biggs-Davison, Peter Blaker, F. Castrillo Mazeres, David Chipp, S. Covarrubias Sanhueza, Hernan Cubillos, Viscount De L'Isle, Paul Dupuis, Georges Egal, J. Erickson, Lord Goronwy-Roberts, Stephen Hastings, Fred C. Ikle, Rajmata of Jaipur, Charles Janson, S. W. B. Menaul, Jaime Perriaux, Carlo Pesenti, W. K. Prendergast, William Rees-Mogg, Juan Pablo Saa, R. Santamaria, Leonard Schapiro, Edgardo Segura, F. P. Serong, Ian Trethowan, Dominique Venner, Colin Welch, Peregrine Worsthorne. Includes some correspondence from 1973 and from 1978 and 1979 (Folder 10)
    - 1978. Correspondents include Raymond Aron, James Burnham, Neil Cameron, Lord Carrington, Winston Churchill, Brian Connell, Robin Day, Viscount De L'Isle, Ronald Duncan, Frederick Forsyth, Richard Francis, Lord Gisborough, Victor Goodhew, Otto von Habsburg, Stephen Haseler, Sir John Killick, Bernard Levin, Earl of Longford, Bryan Magee, Claire Palley, Edgar Pisani, Vittorio Pons, Francis Pym, William Rees-Mogg, Edward Rozek, Erik Rydbeck, Leonard Schapiro, Maurice Temple Smith, Sir Peter Tennant, Margaret Thatcher, Sir Walter Walker, Peregrine Worsthorne. Includes excerpt of a letter from Edward Lansdale to Peter Richards. See also 1977 (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - 1979-1980. Correspondents include Georges Albertini, Julian Amery, Raymond Aron, Richard Bishirjian, Priscilla Buckley, Gonzalo Fernandez de la Mora, Richard Francis, Anthony Hartley, Jesse Helms, Nicko Henderson, Michael Ivens, Ernest Lefever, Richard Lindley, Benjamin Netanyahu, Geoffrey Pattie, Richard Pipes, Francis Pym, Leonard Schapiro, Hugh Seton-Watson, Geoffrey Stewart-Smith, Hugh Thomas, Peter Walker, Albert C. Wedemeyer, John Wilkinson, Paul Wilkinson, Peregrine Worsthorne. See also 1977 (Folder 2)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1980-1991 (Folder 3)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1980-1991 (Folder 4)
  - Thatcher, Margaret
    - 1976-1982 (Folder 5)
    - 1983-1991 (Folder 6)
  - White House, 1980-1986. Correspondents include Richard V. Allen, William P. Clark, Robert C. McFarlane, John M. Poindexter, Edward V. Hickey, Jr. (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous VIPs
    - 1970-1983. Correspondents include Giulio Andreotti, George W. Ball, Zbigniew Brzezinski, George Bush, Lord Caccia, Lord Carrington, Patrick Cormack, Hernan Cubillos, Viscount De L'Isle, Sir Alec Douglas-Home, Malcolm Fraser, Charles de Gaulle, Otto von Habsburg, Jesse Helms, Lord Home, Sir Geoffrey Howe, Henry M. Jackson, Henry A. Kissinger, Nigel Lawson, Prime Minister Markezinis, Richard Nixon, Antoine Pinay, Ronald and Nancy Reagan, Sir Gerald Templer, Margaret Thatcher, William Whitelaw (Box 4., Folder 1)
    - 1980-1985. Correspondents include J. M. Ball, William J. Casey, Francois de Groussouvre, Sir Geoffrey Howe, Antoine Pinay, William A. Wilson (Folder 2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1936-1992
  - General. Freelance writings. Typescript and printed copies
    - Unsigned, 1971-1976 (Box 4., Folder 3)
    - 1936-1963 (Folder 4)
    - 1964 (Folder 5)
    - 1965 (Folder 6)
    - 1966 (Box 5., Folder 1)
    - 1967 (Folder 2)
    - 1968 (Folder 3)
    - 1969 (Folder 4)
    - 1970 (Folder 5)
    - 1971 (Folder 6)
    - 1972 (Folder 7)
    - 1973 (Folder 8)
    - 1974 (Folder 9)
    - 1975 (Box 6., Folder 1)
    - 1976 (Folder 2)
    - 1977 (Folder 3)
    - 1978 (Folder 4)
    - 1979 (Folder 5)
    - 1980 (Folder 6)
    - 1981 (Folder 7)
    - 1982 (Box 7., Folder 1)
    - 1983 (Folder 2)
    - 1985 (Folder 3)
    - 1986 (Folder 4)
    - 1987 (Folder 5)
    - 1988 (Folder 6)
    - 1989 (Folder 7)
    - 1990 (Folder 8)
    - 1991 (Folder 9)
    - 1992 (Folder 10)
  - The Rebels, 1960. Reviews (Folder 11)
  - The Morning After, 1963. Reviews (Folder 12)
  - Neo-Colonialism, 1964. Reviews (Folder 13)
  - Franco, 1967
    - Background material (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - Reviews
      - American (Folder 2)
      - British (Folder 3)
      - French and Belgian (Folder 4)
      - Spanish (Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 6)
  - The Masters of Power, 1969. Reviews (Folder 7)
  - Since Stalin, 1971. Reviews (Folder 8)
  - De Gaulle, 1973
    - American (Folder 9)
    - British, French, and others (Folder 10)
  - A Theory of Conflict, 1974. Reviews (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - The Man Who Lost China, 1976. Reviews (Folder 2)
  - The Strategy of Survival, 1978
    - Correspondence (Folder 3)
    - Reviews (Folder 4)
  - The Minimum State, 1979
    - Correspondence (Folder 5)
    - Reviews (Folder 6)
  - The Price of Peace, 1980. See This War Called Peace, 1984
  - The War Called Peace (Television program), 1980. See This War Called Peace, 1984
  - This War Called Peace, 1984. Reviews (Folder 7)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1975-1977.
  - Agee-Hosenball case. Parliamentary debate transcripts, clippings, and articles relating to the expulsions from Great Britain of Philip Agee and Mark Hosenball (Box 9, Folder 8)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d.
  - One print depicting Belkacem Krim and one depicting Sir Robert Thompson (Envelope Envelope A)